<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <generator uri="https://gohugo.io/" version="0.111.2">Hugo</generator>
    <title>Homelab on Pepo The IT Dog</title>
            <link href="https://blog.pepotheitdog.com/tags/Homelab/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="HTML" />
            <link href="https://blog.pepotheitdog.com/tags/Homelab/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" title="Atom" />
    <updated>2023-07-03T19:54:59+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.pepotheitdog.com/tags/Homelab/</id>
        <entry>
            <title>Homelab playground</title>
            <link href="https://blog.pepotheitdog.com/0post/20230630-homelab/page/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"  hreflang="en" />
            <id>https://blog.pepotheitdog.com/0post/20230630-homelab/page/</id>
            <published>2023-06-30T17:17:09+02:00</published>
            <updated>2023-06-30T17:17:09+02:00</updated>
            <content type="html">
                &lt;p&gt;Long ago, when I wanted to enhance my Virtualization and Automation skills, I explored various options to acquire them beyond my daily work. Product documentation, trainings, and blogs were all helpful for taking initial steps. However, as I delved deeper into numerous subjects, I realized the need to personally test and retain my tests in an isolated environment. By this, I made the decision to purchase my first hardware to set up a homelab&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;gblog-toc gblog-toc__level--2&#34;&gt;
    &lt;nav id=&#34;TableOfContents&#34;&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#homelab-version-1&#34;&gt;Homelab Version 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/nav&gt;
    &lt;hr /&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;



&lt;div class=&#34;gblog-post__anchorwrap&#34;&gt;
    &lt;h2 id=&#34;homelab-version-1&#34;&gt;
        Homelab Version 1
        &lt;a data-clipboard-text=&#34;https://blog.pepotheitdog.com/0post/20230630-homelab/page/#homelab-version-1&#34; class=&#34;gblog-post__anchor clip flex align-center&#34; aria-label=&#34;Anchor Homelab Version 1&#34; href=&#34;#homelab-version-1&#34;&gt;
            &lt;svg class=&#34;gblog-icon gblog_link&#34;&gt;&lt;use xlink:href=&#34;#gblog_link&#34;&gt;&lt;/use&gt;&lt;/svg&gt;
        &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around 2013/2014, I was working at HP as a Technical Consultant, primarily involved in projects related to Windows, Hyper-V, and VMware. My homelab needs at that time revolved around the ability to deploy nested hypervisors, specifically Hyper-V and VMware, along with all the management software associated with these two hypervisors (vCenter, vCOPs, System Center), some HP software, Microsoft Windows Server roles (AD/DNS, CA, FS&amp;hellip;) and a few Microsoft SQL instances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Initially, it seemed that running all these virtual machines would require a significant amount of CPU and memory, while storage and network were not a concern as I didn&amp;rsquo;t anticipate high usage. Moreover, since I was investing money in hardware and didn&amp;rsquo;t want to perform hardware upgrades within a short timeframe, I had to account for future growth in my homelab sizing estimations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the resource requirements, there were other factors that influenced my purchasing decision:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Limited space:&lt;/strong&gt; Living in a flat, free space is valuable, so a smaller hardware solution was preferred.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Noise:&lt;/strong&gt; The hardware had to be placed in the same room where I worked, so it needed to be as silent as possible for the sake of my mental health.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Power comsumption:&lt;/strong&gt; I was mindful of the impact on my utility bills, so power-efficient hardware was a definite advantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, when I searched the market, I came across three options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Servers, Dell PowerEdge or HP ProLiant:&lt;/strong&gt; This option was quickly dismissed due to the excessive noise generated by this type of hardware. Additionally, the high power consumption and space requirements didn&amp;rsquo;t align with my needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intel NUC / Supermicro / Consumer PCs&lt;/strong&gt; This seemed like an interesting option initially. However, after considering the hardware capacity versus cost, limited options for expanding hardware resources, and receiving negative feedback about noise levels (particularly with Supermicro), I decided to discard this option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Professional Workstation:&lt;/strong&gt; Both HP and Dell began releasing new hardware, primarily targeting designers. These workstations combined the advantages of consumer hardware (compact size, low noise) with huge compute resource capacity (support for Intel Xeon processors). Although this hardware was not cheap, it appeared to be the option that best aligned with my requirements, making it the clear winner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After evaluating various models of Professional Workstations, I ultimately chose the HP Z640. I was impressed by how remarkably silent the HP Z640 was, and even after several years, it continues to maintain its quiet operation. In terms of CPU and memory, the HP Z640 offered the capability of accommodating up to two Intel Xeon processors and up to 256GB of memory. This ensured that I would have the potential for future hardware upgrades without encountering any issues, which was one of my requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As mentioned, the price of the HP Z640 was quite high. However, with just one node, I had sufficient resources to build my homelab. Consolidating everything within a single node also reduced the required surface area. Additionally, compared to the NUC/Supermicro option, I would have needed at least three nodes to achieve the same resources. When I evaluated the cost of three nodes versus the HP Z640, the price difference was not significant. By this, I ultimately purchased the HP Z640 with the following specifications:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CPU&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Memory&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SSD Disks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HDD Disks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;2 X Intel(R) Xeon(R) CPU E5-2620 v3 @ 2.40GHz&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;128 Gb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1 X 1Gb Intel nic&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1 X 128 Gb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;1 X 1 Tb&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/0post/20230630-homelab/_assets/media/hp_z640_1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;HP Z640&#34; width=50%; height=auto; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/0post/20230630-homelab/_assets/media/syn_ds415_1.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Synology DS415+&#34; width=50%; height=auto; /&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
            </content>   
                                <category scheme="https://blog.pepotheitdog.com/tags/Homelab" term="Homelab" label="Homelab" />
        </entry>
</feed>
